<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Most strange and terrible astrological predictions and dreadful presages for the ensuing year, 1684 Foretelling what shall happen to several sorts of people in and about the city of London. Together with such mighty wonders that shall happen in this year, the like have not been since Noah's flood. With advice to young men how they may escape the danger. Newly written, and published for the good of all, by S. Trigg.</title>
            <author>Trigg, Stephen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831246</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63236)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2116:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Most strange and terrible astrological predictions and dreadful presages for the ensuing year, 1684 Foretelling what shall happen to several sorts of people in and about the city of London. Together with such mighty wonders that shall happen in this year, the like have not been since Noah's flood. With advice to young men how they may escape the danger. Newly written, and published for the good of all, by S. Trigg.</title>
                  <author>Trigg, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J. Harefinch in Mountague-Court in Little Britain, for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: Most strange and wonderful predictions for the ensuing year, 1684.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predictive astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOST Strange and Terrible ASTROLOGICAL PREDICTIONS AND Dreadful Preſages For the enſuing Year, 1684.</p>
            <p>Foretelling what ſhall happen to ſeveral ſorts of People in and about the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ſuch mighty Wonders that ſhall happen in this Year, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not been ſince <hi>NOAH'S</hi> Flood.</p>
            <p>With Advice to young men how they may eſcape the Danger.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewly Written, and Publiſhed for the good of all, By <hi>S. TRIGG.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Harefinch</hi> in <hi>Mountague-Court</hi> in <hi>Little Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> for the Author. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35709:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35709:2"/>
            <head>Moſt Strange and Wonderful PREDICTIONS For the enſuing Year, 1684.</head>
            <head>To the Readers, Gentle, or Simple.</head>
            <p>SItting upon <hi>Dover</hi> Cliffs, to acquaint my ſelf with the Art of Navigation, and to know the courſe of Tydes; (as the <hi>Dantz</hi> Crows gather on the Sands againſt a Storm) there appear'd on the <hi>Downs</hi> ſuch a flock of Knaves, as by Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Conjectures I began to gather, that this Year 1684. would prove Intemperate, by an extream heat in Summer, inſomuch that the Stones in <hi>Cheap-ſide</hi> ſhall be ſo hot, that many Perſons will fear to go from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> to the <hi>Poultrey</hi> Compter; whereupon I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took me to my Ephemerides, and erecting a Figure, I found that many ſtrange Accidents would fall out this next year 1684. As firſt, <hi>Mercury</hi> being Lord and predominant in the Houſe of Fortune, ſhews, that many Fools ſhall have full Coffers, whilſt wiſe men walk up and down with empty Pockets; and that if <hi>Jupiter</hi> were not joyned to him with a favourable Aſpect, the Butchers of <hi>Eaſt-cheap</hi> ſhould have little to do all the <hi>Lent</hi>-time but make Pricks: Seeing therefore the mighty Wonders that are likely to happen, I have, for the benefit of my Countrey-men, taken in hand to make Prognoſtication, diſcourſing briefly of the Sun and Moon, and the Eclipſes of both, with the dangerous Effects that are like to follow, which if God prevent not, many poor men may faſt on Sundayes for want of Meat, and ſuch as have no ſhooes may go bare-foot: But yet Aſtrology is not ſo certain but it may fail; and therefore many Hoſteſſes, if they be not the more careful, ſhall chalk more this year than their Gueſts wipe out in ſeven: So that I conclude, whatſoever is ſaid by Art, <hi>Sapiens dominabitur Aſtris.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35709:3"/>
               <head>Of the Eclipſes that ſhall happen this Year <hi>1684,</hi> to the mighty terrifying and aſtoniſhing the Beholders.</head>
               <p>IF we may give credit to the Authentical Cenſures of <hi>Albuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> about the Motions of the Celeſtial Bodies, whoſe Influence does excite and procure continual Mutations in the Lower Region, we ſhall find that this year the Moon will be eclipſed, which ſhall happen in one of the twelve Months, and in be totally darkened, ſo the Effects ſhall be the more wonderful; for <hi>Cancer</hi> being the ſole Houſe of the Moon, doth preſage that this year Fruits ſhall be greatly eaten with Caterpillers, as Brokers, Farmers, Flatterers, and other ſuch like Vermin, which, feeding on the Sweat of other mens Brows, ſhall greatly hinder the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spring, and ſpoil the growth of good Herbs, unleſs ſome Northerly Wind from Heaven clear the Trees of ſuch Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms and Catterpillars: <hi>Cancer</hi> being a Watry Sign, and chief Governour of Floods and Streams, fore-ſheweth, that Fiſhmongers if they be not well lookt to, will go down as far as <hi>Graveſend</hi> in Wherries, and yet get but little profit, for their Popiſh Cuſtomers hide themſelves at preſent in <hi>Middletons-Pipes:</hi> Beſides, it ſignifies; that Brewers ſhall make havock of <hi>Thames</hi>-water, and put a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quantity of Liquor to their Malt, to the great detriment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Crazy Ale-Knights, and if it be not well look'd into and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the worſhipful Company of Ale-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nners, may in time prove their fatal overthrow: but in this we have great hopes, that becauſe the Effect cannot ſurpaſs the Cauſe, divers Tapſters ſhall truſt out more than they can get in, though they fill their pots but half full, yet, for want of true dealing, ſhall dye indebted to the Brewer, to his great grief and ſmall ſatisfaction. Thus much of the Watery Sign <hi>Cancer,</hi> only I do adviſe Sea-men to carry two Shirts on Ship-board, for fear of ſix legged Animals, which they muſt be forced to ſpend their time in hunting and murthering to ſave their own Skins whole.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35709:3"/>
                  <head>Of the Eclipſe of the Sun.</head>
                  <p>THE Eclipſe of the Sun, according to <hi>Proclus</hi>'s Opinion, is like to produce many hot and peſtilent Infirmities, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amongſt Somners, Pettifoggers, and ſwinging Evidences, whoſe Faces are combuſt, fiery, deathful, and inflamed with the Juyce of Barley; ſo that if a violent Death do not take away theſe conſuming Malt-worms Barley will be dear. Others ſhall be troubled with hot Rheums in their Heads, and ſuch hot Agues ſhall reign this Year, with ſtrange Fevers and other Calamities, that if the Sun were not placed in a cold Sign, they would again raiſe the price of Wine before <hi>August;</hi> but many good Planets being retrograde, do foretell Lemmons to be plentiful and cheap, that they may be eaten to Bed-ward: and <hi>Mars</hi> being placed near the Sun, ſhews, that many ſhall dye this Summer, old Men and Women, when they can live no longer; and ſome alſo that might live longer if <hi>Jack Ketch</hi> did not put a period to their Maladies. Some Young-men this Year ſhall rejoyce, that have old rich Miſers to their Friends; for the Devil hath made a Decree, that aſſoon as the Doctors, their own Merits and the Prieſts have ſent them to Hell, he'll keep them there, that they ſhall never return to trouble their Heirs for ſpending that on the Devils Back that they pinched out of honeſt poor Peoples Bellies. The Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea ſhall be ſo hot-headed as to quarrel for their Pay, and mutiny, and kill one another; but here Man and Man ſhall quarrel, the Lawyers get their Money and laugh at them for Fools, and thoſe that quarrel moſt ſhall have the Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney's Bleſſing. And further, there will be grumbling as bad as falling out amongſt Church-men; and divers fond Sects in Religion like to be troubleſome both in City and Country. Self-Conceiters and over-holy Counterfeits, that delight in Singularity, ſhall riſe up and deſpiſe Authority, preſuming even to abuſe the higher Powers, if <hi>Saturn</hi> with a frowning influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did not threaten them with <hi>Tyburns</hi> Turns.</p>
                  <p>But whereas the Sun is darkended but by Digits, and that upon the South points, it preſageth great Miſery in <hi>Spain</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35709:4"/>thoſe South Countries: Fryars, Monks, and Jeſuits, ſhall heat themſelves ſo with Confeſſing Harlots, that their Crowns ſhall wax bare of their own Debauchery, to the great impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Barbers; but thoſe Chirurgeons that can cure the Pox may grow rich: and ſuch a peſtilent hypocritical Company as there are of Maſs-mongers, are like to go to the Devil for G—s ſake as the Dog eat the Cuſtard. Further, the Eclipſe falling out in hot Weather, there is like to be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Fleas, that Women will ſit up till Midnight, and longer, doing Execution, in their Smocks and Beds, upon that black Crew of light-heel'd Creatures, and committing Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon them as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did on the <hi>Moors,</hi> or People in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and without any Remorſe: but they muſt remember, What meaſure they made muſt be meaſured to them again ſuddenly.</p>
                  <p>But, as this Eclipſe falls out in the Afternoon, it preſageth, That men ſhall go ſoberer into the Taverns than they ſhall come forth; and thoſe that are drunk and ſleep on the cold Ground, need not fear to dye then in a Sweat. But <hi>Gemini</hi> being combuſt and retrograde, ſheweth, That ſome ſhall have ſo ſore a Sweating, that they may ſell their Hair by the pound to ſtuff Tennis Balls with. If the Beadles be careful this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, it may be hoped that <hi>Thieving-Lane</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> may be cleanſed from evil Faries, and that honeſt Women may live there quietly, not fearing Whip or Cart. I find the like of the Altitude of <hi>Whetſtones-Park</hi> and <hi>Dog and Bitch Lane,</hi> as well as <hi>Southampton</hi> Buildings, the which places, before the Reſtauration was moiſtened with ſuch precious Water, that the Whores cannot as yet depart, becauſe <hi>Venus</hi> preſageth the ſame; and ſhe being retrograde and ſlow, leaves them there to the Power of thoſe Conſtables that dare diſturb them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have drawn in too many Young-men Noviſes, to their utter Ruine and Deſtruction. And further, it is to be noted, Many ſtrange Children ſhall be born, who ſhall live ſo ſtrangely, that when they come to be Biſhop't they have not Wit enough to know their own Fathers, but from ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, ſhall have their Fingers like Lime-twiggs, to get their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings with five an a Reach; and ſome ſhall have Feet like Hares, and ſhall trudge from Poſt to Pillar till they take up
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35709:4"/>Beggars Buſh for their Lodging, others ſhall have good Noſes to ſmell Feaſts of others Coſts; likewiſe divers Women this Year ſhall have two Tongues, to the terrible Grief of them that marry them, uttering in their Fury ſuch rough-caſt Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that Knave and Slave ſhall be but Holy-day Words to their Husbands. Whereas this fearful Eclipſe doth endure one hour and a half, it ſignifies Womens Love to their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſhall be very ſhort; and ſome ſo momentary, that it ſhall hardly endure form the Church to the Bride-houſe, the Air is ſo variable this Year. Alſo it is to be noted, that Hens, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, Geeſe, and Pullets, ſhall not frequent Poor-mens Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but fly even roaſted, from the Spits to rich Churls and Gluttons, to pamper them up againſt next <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi> Much more might be ſaid, but I end thus, deſiring them that have good Cloaths to wear them, and thoſe that have good Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, to eat, and thoſe that have Money may take their Eaſe and be quiet, and not meddle nor make, but live till they dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the ſecond Eclipſe of the Moon.</head>
                  <p>THE ſecond Eclipſe of the Moon will be before the 31th of <hi>December</hi> or not this Year 1684. I conceive it will be ſeen but little in our <hi>Meridian,</hi> therefore the Effects cannot be very prejudicial to us nor any of our Clime. But yet as the Body of the Moon is never obſcure either in part or whole, but it ſhews ſome dangerous Effects to follow, ſo I mean to ſet down briefly what may be look'd for. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, let the <hi>Danes</hi> look to it, and be ſure to ſteel their Noſes well, and drink good ſtore of ſtrong Liquor to heat their Blood, that they may well keep out the <hi>French</hi> and cold Weather, for they are both bad; and the wary <hi>Hollander</hi> muſt be careful, for they have been too bold, to meddle with ſuch things as have been too high for them. The Lyon ſleeps; he may wake: the <hi>French</hi> are proud, and fear not; but their Time is nigh, and Plum-Porridge is good all the Year, but in Faſhion at <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> with the Pipes, Cards, Roaſt-Beef, and Dice, and many a Song, and carouſing Night and Day with ſome that their Wives and Children ſuffers Hunger and Cold.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35709:5"/>But as the Eclipſe is South, and in the eighth Houſe, ſo there is like to be in <hi>France</hi> a great Dearth of honeſt Men, and few there left, but their. Hope may periſh, and their Enterprize come to Shame; for there was a Prophecy found in an old Book, which is likely to prove true, <hi>viz. The Tree that God hath not planted ſhall be rooted-up in a time when least thought of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some curious Aſtronomers of late days, more prophetical than judicial, do affirm, That after ſuch Phiznomizes there ſhall ſtrange Sects ariſe; as if ſome of Goodman-<hi>Pope</hi>'s old Saints ſhould come again to ſet the People a madding after new Whimſies in Religion, and with ſuch fond Humours in their Brains, that diverſe Fools ſhall become ſelf-conceited, and grounding their witleſs Opinions on ſome heretical Fancy, ſhall ſeek to ruminate Authority; and ſo firmly ſhall they ſtand, that though many of them are deſtroyed, their Diſciples ſhall grow up, like Graſs, innumerable, that Tyburn will be hard put to it; were it not that the Moon being in <hi>Taurus,</hi> that governs Neck and Throat, ſhews that the Squinancy ſhall reign amongſt them, and ſtrangle many by conſequence, otherwiſe they would run retrograde to the year forty two, and then run direct and ſwift in motion thereby thinking to increaſe in number: but ſtay—<hi>Capricorn</hi> is a Sign wherein <hi>Luna</hi> is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reſident, which prognoſticateth great Miſchiefs amongſt horned Beaſts, declaring that the Butchers ſhall commit willful murther upon many Rams, Sheep, Oxen, and Cows, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, if they did not pay too dear for them; but many that take them where they find them, ſhall certainly come to make up their Accounts with Jack Catch for their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, (or for want of it) becauſe they always ſay, that plain dealing will dye a Beggar: but this we are certainly ſure of, that for want of it many hang like Dogs: obſerve likewiſe the Act made, That he that wipes his Noſe and hath none, is to forfeit his plain Face; and all ſuch who are jealous of their Wives without cauſe, deſerve the horns to make them amends.</p>
                  <p>And as the Eclipſe is far from <hi>Piſces,</hi> it doth prognoſticate that there will be great ſtore of ſtinking Fiſh at <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> and at <hi>Quinborough</hi> their Oyſter-Boats ſhall go nigh to be as full of Knaves as honeſt Men: beſides, a great many fiſh-wives this Year are like to prove arrant Scolds, and ſome of them drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35709:5"/>Wh—s, and ſhall take Strangers into their Husband's Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by day-light, and ſwear they may do it as well as Ladies; and commend their great Freedoms, ſaying, They are the beſt Houſwives that lye in bed to ſave their Shooes; and that a Plaiſter of warm Guts, a Toaſt and good Liquor, with a good Fire, is far better than to freeze with Cold: and that a Cup of good Ale, a piece of old Cheeſe and a Toſt, or a piece of pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Beef and a Bag-pudding is very hearty, and Plum-pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Roſt-beef, Minc'd Pyes, Turkeys, Geeſe, Capons, and ſuch like good Cheer, with a Glaſs of good Wine, is far better to end the Year withall than a thump on the back with a Stone.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now I ſhall ſpeak ſomething of Mans Inclinations and Diſpoſitions for the whole year, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And firſt, of the Winter-Quarter, ſo far as by Art I can conjecture.</head>
               <p>WHatever <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſays, it matters not, for I ſay it begins ſooner with poor men than with rich: becauſe of the malignant Influence of <hi>Saturn,</hi> whoſe malevolent nature is ſuch, that thoſe who have neither Cloathes, Money, nor Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ſhall want not only Meat and Drink, but alſo Wood and Coals, and be ready to ſtarve with Cold, whilſt rich men may ſit by a good Fire, with Apples and Ale and Ginger: And though the Seaſon be cold and flegmatick, ſome will be afraid of the Cold, and ſit all day long at Cards, Dice or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, whilſt their poor Wives and Children want Neceſſaries at home by reaſon of their Folly. But in regard that I find two of the ſeven Planets in Capricorn, <hi>viz.</hi> the Winter-ſign, <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Piſces, Mars</hi> in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> it doth certainly ſignifie, that many men and Women, for want of Wine and ſtrong Drink, ſhall go ſober to bed ſore againſt their Wills; and alſo that Sea-men ſhall have very ill luck if their Ships ſtrike againſt Rocks, or ſtick in the Sands. Here likewiſe <hi>Saturn</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde in <hi>Leo,</hi> ſhews, that many rich men may loſe their Purſes by High-way-men, and the poor be weather-beaten
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35709:6"/>by Uſury and Extortion: But <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gragated in <hi>Sagittary,</hi> ſhews, that they that have no Shirts in time will be lowſie, and yet ſave the charge of waſhing: and Water men for want of Fares may ſit ſtill and blow their Fingers ends, notwithſtanding the many thouſands of <hi>French</hi> come hither of late, if they have not ſaved a penny as well for a froſty day as a rainy: Alſo Eeles will in all probability be dear, if there be but few taken: but Powts will be plentiful in all places; eſpecially in thoſe Cities and Countries where Women cannot have their wills, and maundring broth ſcold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot, although it be cold Weather. Now as far as can be gheſs'd by the divers Configurations of the Stars, and their Significations, there is nothing more plain, than that they that have no Fire this Winter-ſeaſon cannot be very hot.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Spring-Quarter.</head>
                  <p>THe Spring is comfortable to all Animals: the Sun is got out of <hi>Piſces,</hi> and entered into <hi>Aries,</hi> the Ram, the Houſe of <hi>Mars,</hi> and the Suns exaltation, by which I find many Scholars to have dull pates for want of timely Preferment, becauſe the monied Blades have all the Livings, and he that hath no Mony ſhall have no living, which makes ſome ſcratch where it does not itch, for kiſſing goes always by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: but <hi>Jupiter</hi> being now on his way to Sagittary, fiery, and in his exaltation, ſhews, that when he's there he is reſolv'd to mend all, and that Reward ſhall no more go backwards, nor Honour upon his Head, but many ſhall receive Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments according to their Merits. And according to <hi>Proclus</hi> his Opinion, Women are likely to grow wilful, yet their Husbands muſt be content; and Butchers will ſell their Meat as dear as they can, and many keep their Sheeps heads ſo long that at laſt they are forced to throw them away, though their Wives preſerve their Horns; and ſome men ſhall be ſo wedded to Swines Fleſh, that they ſhall never be without a Sow in their Houſe as long as they live.</p>
                  <p>The Spring or Vernal Quarter is naturally hot and moiſt, which ſhews the ſprouting out of Trees, Herbs and Weeds alſo; it likewiſe ſheweth old men to be teſty and froward, and that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35709:6"/>crafty Knaves need no Brokers; but the Sun being in his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities in <hi>Aries</hi> portendeth much evil to thoſe who have taken the Fleet and Kings Bench on purpoſe to defraud their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, which Places were for no other purpoſe but to relieve the oppreſſed, and poor in neceſſity, but of late have been made as bad as a Den of Thieves, by the moſt abominable Cheats and Coſenages daily committed, to the aſtoniſhment and admiration of all honeſt men; that the Creditor may ſee his Mony ſpent, the Jaylor inricht, and himſelf grow poor, without remedy; which in all honeſt mens thoughts is little better than robbery, or as the old Saying is, Robbing <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul:</hi> but <hi>Jupiter</hi> and the Sun being both juſt and kingly Planets, foreſheweth the ſtopping up, and ferretting theſe Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es out of their holes, wherein they lye and upbraid their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, to their utter ruine oftentimes. Now becauſe <hi>Aquarius</hi> hath ſomething to do in this Quarter, it is to be feared that the Vintners will put more Water in their Wine than formerly, to the great dammage, if not utter overthrow of many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient red Noſes: and out of the old ſtock of Hereſie may be broacht ſome new Schiſmatical Opinions, that may yet diſturb ſome honeſt men that mean well: but certain it is, that there is likely to ſwarm ſuch a huge ſwarm of Hypocrites, that an honeſt man will be hard to be found, eſpecially in <hi>White-Friars</hi> or the mint in <hi>Southwark.</hi> But oh! you generation of wicked Oſtlers, worſe Vermin than any, who rob poor Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and greaſe their Teeth that they cannot eat their meat when they ſtand at Livery; by all the foregoing Configurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Celeſtial Signs, this I prognoſticate againſt you, That he that dyes amongſt you dies a Thief, and he that lives lives a Knave; and if he leaves not thoſe cheating tricks he ſhall die a Beggar. I muſt not hide this notable Secret, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> being in <hi>Aſpect</hi> with <hi>Luna,</hi> diſcovereth, that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther growing warm many ſhall drink more than they bleed, and Taylors ſhall ſteal nothing but what is brought to them, Poulteres ſhall be much peſtered with ſtinking Fowl Conies, to the anoyance of their Neighbours, and their own diſprofit. Butchers Dogs hate Lent, and ſome Apprentices that have hard Maſters will be much trouble with the Shoulders ake, more eſpecially when <hi>Sol</hi> enters <hi>Gemini.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35709:7"/>
                  <head>Of Comets in general.</head>
                  <p>IT has been the long received Opinion of all the famous Aſtrologers, That Comets do always portend, to ſome Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Places in the World, where their Influence ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, War, Fire, Famine, Peſtilence, Tumults, Inſurrections, Invaſions, inundations, or what ever elſe they pleaſe to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine; but I ſay, ſo far as by Art I lawfully may, That many People (if they do not leave drinking and live temperately) ſhall have wonderful ruby Faces, and great red Noſes, which ſhall ſhine ſo powerfully, that in a dark night, if their Eyes be good, they may ſerve inſtead of a Link to light them home; and be as neceſſary as Touch-Wood in their Pockets to light their Tobacco: and many People that have great ſtore of Wood and Coals, may if they pleaſe keep good Fires at Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas; but thoſe that are Frequenters of Whetſtones Park, Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, Lutenor's-Lane, and ſuch like Places, by reaſon of the exceſſive heat of that Climate, (although it be cold Winter) yet ſhall carry Fire in their Tails, to the Deſtruction of their whole Bodies if they do not in time call for the Aſſiſtance of an able Chirurgeon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Conjunctions.</head>
                  <p>BUt ſince we are now falling under the Effects of the moſt famous and remarkable Conjunctions of the Superior Planets, that has happened many hundred years, therefore we may well expect moſt wonderful Events in many Places, not only of <hi>Europe,</hi> but elſewhere; that is to ſay, many Single People of both Sexes ſhall be mightily deſirous to be in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and marry in haſte, but they may repent at leiſure: Alſo thoſe that are purblind or Moon-ey'd will hardly ever look right forwards, and thoſe that cannot hold their water will be ſubject to piſs in Bed; thoſe that ſwear ſhall catch no Fiſh, and they that angle in dirty Ditches may happily catch Frogs; thoſe that have no money need not fear robbing; but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35709:7"/>they that can get no Cloaths, may certainly go naked, as well as thoſe that hope for dead Folks Shooes go barefoot.</p>
                  <p>I do likewiſe prognoſticate from the various Configurations at the time of writing theſe Predictions, There ſhall reign a cruel Diſeaſe in poor mens purſes, but it ſhall be with Emptineſs; inſomuch that ſome ſhall be ready to cut out their pockets, greatly fearing they may never have more occaſion to uſe them. Thoſe that have taken great Cold may be troubled with the Cough, and thoſe that are ſick will have worſe Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs than thoſe that are well, although neither the one nor the other can digeſt a Ten-penny Nail, or a Bag of Tenter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooks, unleſs they are well butter'd. There will certainly be many Scolds at Billingſgate, and as many well qualified men at the Bear-garden. There will be many Knaves belong to the Cuſtom-houſe, Exciſe, Chimneys, beſides the Knaves that ſell <hi>Quinborough</hi> Oyſters, and thoſe that fill the Oyſtersbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels half full of Weeds inſtead of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Oyſters. The Knights of the Poſt, if <hi>Mercury</hi> prove true, may do great execution and get Money, and the Butchers make havock of Flies. Millers and Weavers ſhall be as theeviſh as ever, and Lawyers and Phyſicians no changelings, that which ſoever walks firſt, as good comes after. But woe to you Gold-lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, but that you only cheat them that have Money, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe your Trade were next to that of Pick-pockets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, to get eleven pence in the Shilling honeſtly. Woe to you Shoomakers, that make Shooes little ſtronger than Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and plead for your excuſe that they are for Miſſes, that ride in Coaches, or lye on their backs Night and Day with their fore legs upwards, and their Shoos off, if they be anything dirty: To theſe inchanting Serpents many Gallants ſo often reſort to pay their Courtſhips, that in ſmall time they are forc'd to go dine with Duke <hi>Humphry,</hi> and then the thoughts of their Debaucheries increaſes their Miſeries. A good Leſſon for young men to learn, that the wickedneſs of whoring, gaming and drinking, is the Deſtruction of thouſands: It takes away a mans Reputation, good Name and Credit, makes him a ſcorn and a by-word, hated and ſlighted of all: a Beaſt, worſe than a Dog; for a Dog doth but according to kind, but what a ſhame is it for a man to degrade his own Soul, to make the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35709:8"/>Temple of the holy God a Swill-tub, a ſtinking naſty draugh-houſe, and his Mouth, that ſhould praiſe the living God, his Privy: through which you ſhorten your dayes in this Life, and endanger your Souls in the life to come.</p>
                  <p>Therefore young men, learn to be wiſe, look to your ways, and take notice how many, for not fearing God and ſerving him, have fallen to ruine, and Repentance come to late; but let it be your care to lead ſuch a Life that you need not repent of that folly that many before you have committed; aſſuring your ſelves that the hearty Sacrifices of thoſe that are young and luſty, and in the prime of their Youth, God will accept: Serve God while you are young, and he will never leave you when you are old: and by this means you ſhall eſcape all the Dangers that can threaten Mortals.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Mars</hi> being exalted in <hi>Capricorn,</hi> and entring the firſt term of <hi>Venus,</hi> ſtirrs up much Debauchery amongſt Lewd People, and makes them hate to hear of any thing that is good: And likewiſe denotes, that abundance of luſty young men, that have very good Trades, and might live otherwiſe, if they were not lazy, ſhall be ſuffered to keep Ale-houſes, and to bear Offices, to the great encouragement of Idleneſs, and perhaps ruining of many thouſands; which the lower Stars may remedy if they pleaſe to be ſo benevolent: but in many places, through their favourable Aſpect, the Event of Licenſing ſuch People to lick the Spiggot, only brings Profit to the Juſtices Clerk, and many the Halter; Whereas, take away Idleneſs, and the Cauſe of it, all other inconveniences will be remov'd, our Nation flouriſh, and all be happy: but the many private Bottle-houſes, and Gaming-houſes brings ſudden ruin and deſtruction to Youth: At this <hi>Jupiter</hi> thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but is not heard: becauſe falſe <hi>Mercury</hi> having his Fall in <hi>Piſces,</hi> denotes, that many Men will rather give credit to idle Livers and falſe Teſtimonies, than to ſearch out the Truth: and by their being corrupted, the old Proverb is verified, That one man may better ſteal a Horſe than another look over the Hedge.</p>
                  <p>The World is drawing to an end with old men, and yet ſome will not amend their Lives, though they are daily call'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35709:8"/>upon, and allarm'd, yet will not turn: but let ſuch men know, that the Conſtellations of Heaven do abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that there is a time coming when it ſhall be happy for thoſe who are found well-doing.</p>
                  <p>And now to conclude, Let us all both Old and Young de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from Evil and do good, ſerve God to our utmoſt Power, love and honour our King, chearfully obey all that are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over us, and love one another; this is a ſure way to be happy both here and hereafter. And thus I conclude my Predictions for the Year 1684.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
